welcome to the stoa
the stoa is a digital campfire where we
cohere
and dialogue about what matters most at
the knife's edge
of what's happening now
welcome to the dark stoa with pat ryan
i'm your host daniel kazanjian and
for the uninitiated these events tend to
deal with
slightly more challenging subject matter
sometimes they prompt existential horror
and sometimes they blow your mind a
little bit and they make you think
so consider yourself warned
the structure for tonight is pretty
simple in a moment i'm going to hand it
over to pat
and he's going to take us through a
really interesting mind-bending
presentation
and throughout this presentation i
encourage everybody to write down any
questions that come up any ways that you
want to challenge pat anything you don't
understand
and then we'll shift over to q a and
we'll
send it and we can
have some dialogue with pat ryan
um yeah and without further delay
i gave you pat ryan
howdy folks welcome back thanks for
coming back um
the last string of episodes have been
fairly
oh first is my volume okay
okay great um first a couple
s episodes of this have been kind of
like
uh uh this one i'm going to pump the
brakes a bit um because i'm sure if
you've been following along you might be
asking yourself the question does he
have any morality at all
um the answer is going to be answered uh
with this presentation which is called
the morality machine
belief as a technology so the word
belief is pretty
loaded everyone has their own personal
definition of it and i'm going to do my
best to fight each and every one of you
on it
and uh so bear with me as i go along i'm
going to attempt to
explain how
how neural networks actually work
without ever getting into the
technicality of it
because they're pretty complicated by
themselves in principle they're simple
but if you're not initiated to that kind
of thing is pretty daunting
they make a lot of assumptions and
unfortunately neural networks themselves
aren't following any type of
systematized logical approach
it's all very haphazardly discovered as
we go along
so i'm going to do my best to frame how
a neural network works exclusively in
philosophical terms and that should
hopefully be a useful bridge
to then explore some of our
hair trigger inclinations when it comes
to questions
of moral decision making
um and
that's as best of a summary as i can
come up with let me share the screen and
let's get started
oh no you have to enable screen sharing
sir
excellent let us begin
cool let me get all this stuff
situated
oh that's wrong go back there we go
okay uh i think we're good here
okay uh morality machine if anybody's
played chrono trigger
one of my favorite games this scene blew
my mind when i was a kid
uh also i'm still experimenting with a
vpn sponsorship so if you want to
have a crack at beating some quantum
computers
wild apparently that's going to be a
thing um try these guys out you can qr
code this
or there's a url here okay so
moving on
okay so
we're going to talk about categorical
correspondence which is a fancy way of
saying
um does this category correspond to this
category
now it doesn't have to be a tight
category if i was to say
shapes correspond to triangles that's a
that's a correspondence
if i was to say
[Music]
mugs of coffee correspond to cats i'd
have to work a little bit harder to make
the correspondence
so i'm basically i'm this is about
making
taking a concept and figuring out what
category that concept belongs
in is what we're kind of always doing
with logic and trying to determine these
things
now you can do hard categorization say
this thing is absolutely in this
category
or you can do kind of a gaussian
categorization where you say this is
about 40
in this category and 30 in this other
category
and this is the kind of rash now we use
to start
evaluating moral systems to begin with
we always start in this typing
categorical process
and it's made more relevant especially
in a time
when we have surrounded ourselves in so
much technology that is all just a
direct extension of set theory anyways
so from sit you get type category and so
forth and so on
so the
we have put ourselves in this position
where
our morality is now being shaped
not only by us but by our desire to make
our morality representable within
machines
we're able to do that because we have
the internet the internet is a way where
we can reach out and poke one another
and say
did i poke you and get the behavior i
want if the answer is no then the poking
will continue
and as a result we just keep iterating
and coming up with these new ways to
jam our morality in these machines and
the way
we're doing that right now as of 2020
is through neural networks so i'm going
to walk you through it real quick
and if you know how this stuff works
please bear with me i'm doing my best to
bridge it in philosophical terms
okay so let's say i have a brightness
sensor
it's uh you've all seen these things
they you you walk near a garage and it
kicks on a light because of a motion
sensor
right that's that's kind of a brightness
sensor or an ir sensor or anything along
those lines so there's something out
there
reading light or heat or something and
as it's exposed to that heat it then
represents the intensity in a numeric
form it could say
uh well it's about let's say that 256 is
as bright as it can handle
and zero is as dark as i can right so
everything in between
is a gradient of brightness right from
zero which is absolute dark to 256 which
is absolute brightness right
so in this case i have a set of these
values
this is the brightness that the
brightness sensor just happened to get
in some
random sample of time that i just picked
for convenience okay
so what i'm doing is each one of these
lines
will carry what's called a weight
meaning i'm going to say hey 256 to the
dark
quite for um for the assessment of how
dark 256 is
there's going to be a weight here that
explains
exactly what that means so 256 remember
that's as bright as it gets
to the dark categorizer it's going to
say that's zero dark
because this is braze against now if i
if i sent
0 to the dark categorizer that would be
dark right so each one of these lines
carries the bias
that the categorizer uses to make the
evaluation
so if i sent it uh 128 which is half of
256 i send it to the bright categorizer
it says that's 50 bright and if i send
it to dark it's also going to say it's
dark so that's pretty straightforward
right so i say
64 in this case i send it to bright that
should be around if i can do my math
right that's like
75 no it's 25 bright and 75
dark right so it's pretty simple it's
just a formal way of representing
um the weight and what comes out of it
so what we're doing is we're taking
these events these brightness events and
we're encoding the value
wow that's a terrible place to put that
uh we're encoding the value
as a category basically that's all we're
doing here right so if you see these
graphs
you now know what these graphs are
actually now i'm not going to get into
hidden layers because i don't want to
chase anyone out in fact i'm going to
save that for last so just
pump your brakes a bit right so just to
walk us through um
this is my training i'm training my
categorizers to understand this stuff so
that when
i hit it with a value it's never seen
before in this case 76 because i didn't
start with 76.
what's going to happen is i'm going to
run it through this network and it's
going to
tell me that it's 29 bright the
categorizer will tell me that in the
dark it'll tell me the inverse
so pretty straightforward kind of as
best as i can put it so we're doing a
categorical assessment of a new event
this new
76 is a new event that's a new
brightness hasn't been there before
the machine uh the categorizers are able
to say
it's this bright or it's this dark right
pretty straightforward so let's switch
it up a bit
let's make it about morality instead of
light and dark let's do good and evil
now we're going to open up all kinds of
problems because i just said the two
magic words that make this a big problem
what is evil what is good well that
depends upon what behavior are you
are you quantifying as morality you know
what's what's the value here are you
256 what 256 dollars you donated
is it 256 times you hugged your kid what
what is this value representing here
right
so we can have infinite questions about
what these numbers should be these
things will work
there's no doubt about that if i if
these things will absolutely categorize
whatever the hell i
train it so now we got to step back and
say what are we what are you
categorizing here really
i mean is can you even do this type of
thing
so that's like red flag number one
that's uh
behavior as quantified morality who
who's labeling these values right who's
coming up with these numbers
and who's actually able to like agree to
those numbers and comport to them right
so the problems are starting to amass
from the junk
if i give it 76 using the same exact
model from the previous slide
then 76 is 29 good
so whatever people say well it's not
about good and evil it's the gray area
in between
congratulations i've given that gray
area a number
it's now 29 you are 29 good i can now
measure your greatness right
so now our morality is starting to um
it's starting to turn into an
interesting thought experiment before
morality was the
measure of man's inaction or man's
action with
itself and other people and the world
and the universe and being in reason and
trying to formulate all that stuff and
now
i'm this is how machines seem this is
how ai will
take these deep problems that we've
enamored ourselves with
and it will spit it out into these
distributions these percentage
distributions
and that's what it's currently doing
right now regarding how
how much hate speech exists in a in a
post
how much uh how offensive a meme is
um is this is a is a
piece of web content uh
uh of um you know the basic stuff uh
offensive and stuff like that right
so that may sound good and that's how
they sell it they're eliminating h
speech and that kind of thing but
this is what it looks like i mean this
is what it actually looks like at the
mathematical scale
which is again we know the problems of
trying to
quantify morality as behavior values if
the problems don't go away
when we extend and we we go further it
gets worse
in fact um so
what i've tapped into is this this
unending holy war about
not only the quantification of of the
moral behavior you're trying to measure
now we talk about
categorization errors that 76 is 29
good well turns out the fan club of 76
they're really pissed about that rating
they know that they're better than 29
in fact they have the historical
evidence they can say god damn it we are
not 29
good we are at least 80 so now you have
these holy wars about the outcomes of
these things to begin with because your
priors were all wrong your values were
then here they come oh i got a million
litany of reasons as to why this value
is bad
they're just gonna yell at you all day
and oh by the way they also have
unaccountable influence in silicon
valley so they can ban you from paypal
and stripe and
your life basically so
these people are very upset and this is
just
the stereotype i'm throwing her out
there because the internet's a lovely
place
um they're very upset about this it's 29
right this is bad
they they are not happy with that
numbers in fact it's
there's systemic reasons and
socioeconomic conditions and
they just keep throwing just books and
books of
perverted sociology at you until you
just say fine i'll change a
number right
so how do i change a number i have to
calculate the loss
that's a math term and i apologize but i
have to calculate the loss
or more correctly in philosophical terms
the categorization error
meaning that 20 that 76 was not supposed
to be 29
because this person's real pissed off
and they put a gun to my head so i
better make it 80
so how do i do that well i got to take
the 29 percent that is that it's done i
got to run this creature through it and
then i can calculate my loss
so i got my loss and now i have to
reapply it back
to my categorization methodology
so that looks like this i take my loss
and i start affecting my weights
remember these are the weights these are
the things that inform the
categorization
they say yes okay 256 means this
and evil in 256 means this and good but
our
the person who put the gun to our heads
says uh that's that's mean
and they're calling these things racist
and these things aren't racist
this this is the problem right here it's
not these things
these things are just doing whatever you
train them to do it's not even
calculating the losses the problem it's
not even the weights or the biases that
are the problem it's actually this
insane idea that you can quantify
morality
that's where the problem is but we don't
care we don't want to do that we suck
way too many billions of dollars in
these machines and god damn it i want to
return on investment so we're going to
tweak the loss instead
so we're going to take that loss and
we're going to apply it to all of our
weights
and now suddenly 76 is 80 good but we
did we did it we hacked the numbers
right right we uh we represented the the
exception
in our moral framework and we've baked
it in the machine so when the machine
sees the 76 again it will make the
appropriate categorization which means
the gun that's against our head
will back off slowly right so we did it
right we're not making moral assessments
anymore we're compensating for people
with power
well now we're no longer talking about
morality we did it right we have now
jumped the shark we don't want to keep
we we don't want to catch ourselves jump
in the shark because that gun can come
back any time you know you can come in
your birthday
tuesday you don't want that right
so
ah damn it it's not good enough
eighty percent wasn't good enough
she puts it higher she was at ninety
percent it's
she has a million more reasons now why
that's like oh god now we gotta do this
again
oh okay fine all right we'll just apply
the laws again all right we know how to
do this
it's not the end of the world we know
how to do this we're going to do it
okay so we're going to take the law
since something's interfering with
humanist progress and it's up to us
this is our holy crusade to do this we
got this people we got this we know how
to do this
so we take the loss because we know how
to take the loss and we know how to
apply it
to the next iteration each one of these
is it's like an iteration of every time
i apply the loss
i'm applying the loss to change weights
so the categories are better
so let's do it again and we're going to
keep on doing it we're going to keep on
doing it so we get that number we're
looking for we're going to just
we're going to we're going to hack this
damn thing we're going to get that
number
and we got this we we got this we know
we got this
wait hold on what do you mean the
percentage change zero
zero zero one hold up whoa whoa whoa
whoa oh gosh she's back
oh no like what are we going to do about
this i i changed the numbers i did the
thing
i did the thing i i made the loss like
what the hell what did i do wrong
what is going on here well now in
addition to compensating for someone
with a gun
uh we are now fighting the machine
itself
so now we're not even talking about
morality anymore that's just how we gave
that up
like two slides ago right now we're
talking about now we gotta fight the
machine
okay so now i promise to keep the
technical away
i have to delve into this a little bit
uh just
this is the time to write questions if
you have them so
what's going on here well i've been
showing you the categorizers as like the
that's like the end of the neural
network there's actually these things
called hidden layers in between them
i don't want to get into them because i
think the name itself is confusing for
people who don't know it so what i'm
going to do is i'm going to represent
those hidden layers as
feature detectors so um think of a
feature as
uh think of a feature as
if there if there are categories for
good and evil then a feature would be a
subset of properties
for what is good and what is bad and
that's just that's just the wrong
definition that's the best i got right
um okay so we're going to go through
these features
about the the categorical the means in
which the categorical
the categorical correspondence is
evaluated that's what these futures are
doing
so for example we're going to pump our
numbers in and the neural network has
come up with
four a layer made of four nodes and it
just turns out
that they happen to represent
these kind of things i'm just throwing
names on there just for now just for
labeling and comprehension reasons
you'll never get labels in an absolute
network by the way you can't actually
examine this stuff um
so like maybe maybe nervousness is a
part of morality or emotional sentiment
averaging or
some weird pattern some some
correspondence
correlation mechanism right and then
that passes to the next layer
i'm just going to say you know maybe
this layer is looking for these things
and then it passes to the next layer and
maybe it's looking for these things and
when it goes through this whole thing
that's how it makes its actual
categorization
so you start with your 256 it's jump in
here it's it's giving you the it
jumps here does the product to here the
product to here and then
you get your evaluations and so forth
like i said these are just placeholders
to convey a concept
uh if you want to look into how hidden
layers actually work feel free
there are way better resources out there
than i'm currently providing but this is
just to demonstrate again our problem is
that the person has the gun to our head
and we weren't able to change percentage
and we got to change the percentage or
we're going to shoot us
so what the hell right so what's
happening
oh now she's back and now she's actually
in the layers and she's saying well this
doesn't represent all of reality
this doesn't represent all the moral
things that we could have infinitely
more layers
we could have layers for i don't know
how many giraffes did you lick
last week like that's a moral thing
right we could throw that in there i
mean we may have to
she has a gun what are we going to do so
all right
we'll get to the problem i try to tell
her i say we can't add more layers
because that's actually the problem it
won't do anything she doesn't get it
she doesn't understand it she just wants
the moral victory she wants the
political victory right
so the reason why adding more layers
doesn't work
it's because a thing called vanishing
gradients vanishing gradients are a
if you remember the last talk where i
focused on infinitesimals
infinitesimals are back and they are
causing problems
so we calculate our laws
uh which we've done uh just just as we
do because we're trying to correct
and then what happens is the losses say
losses happen to be like 0.1 for
whatever reason
so we apply it backwards we propagate it
backwards into these weights
to change it so that when this spits out
values we say
well your values need to be modified a
bit and so we can get better results
here but in the process of doing so it's
it may then apply
a little bit less to the layer behind it
and now
this one spits out evaluations we modify
that and it puts it in here
then this modification might happen the
moment
this happens you're you're done
it's over because this change is so tiny
it's so infinitesimally vanishing
that any change here or here or here or
here
because the change here is so small
when it propagates through you're going
to be stuck with the same value over and
over again
because you have to do heavy changes
here in order to get this network to do
its categorization properly
if the if the if the loss compensation
goes here and it's so tiny
then nothing you do can ever matter no
amount of layers you add no amount of
nodes you add could ever change the
outcome of your good evil analysis
so this is what i said this is what i
mean when you're fighting the machine
you're fighting just the way that this
whole thing is structured
um and if this happens you get the
vanishing gradient
and that's why she's mad she's really
upset she doesn't understand the vanish
ingredient she just wants some moral
victory so i try to sit her down and say
hey to vanishing gradient
she doesn't care she puts two guns in my
head because goddammit now she really
needs the answer
i was like okay all right i'm fine fine
i'll hack it i will come up with some
crazy hack
we can make this work we'll make this
work i swear to god just
just i i give it one more time i say
that
i'm just saying it became prematurely
incandescent you change the weights
between the wear
the the layers and it has no effect so
adding more like i tell her all this
stuff but
fine it i'll just i'll just hack it
right i'll come up with a deep belief
network right so i'm going to use a deep
belief network to solve this problem
because i just i just get the guns out
of here
so the same setup but instead what i'm
doing
instead of calculating the loss and
applying it in individually in sequence
backwards
what i'm going to do is i'm going to say
okay well let me let me change how these
are processing
these are called restricted boltzmann
machines
and what that's a fancy way of saying
that um
the inputs here lead to a certain output
here but it can also reconstruct the
output to regenerate the input
so what this means is instead of just
doubly passing things along
what this will do is it will come it
will basically
process the inputs in a way
that is locally relevant to itself
so it's not sitting here waiting for the
next
activity it's able to come up with an
equilibrium within itself and this is
true for each layer and the reason
that's important
is because when we calculate our loss we
then do it
fine-tune it everywhere at the same time
not backwards in the sense where it hits
here then it hits here and then it's
here we can actually fine tune the loss
difference
completely differently and so by doing
it this way
you end up in a very unique position
where you can add more layers freely
and you don't ever hit that problem with
the vanishing gradient
just completely eliminated so you can
fine-tune each one of these layers who
are
taking the responsibility of
categorizing the inputs themselves
now this solution is useful but it's
also incredibly difficult to train
even in this example you'll see the
problems you'll say well
um this is probably a good tribal way of
looking at the problem and then the
religious people over here have a way
and then the
humanists have a way and how do i
synchronize all these people
well that's exactly the same problem
you'll have here if you try to
if you think of this in a philosophical
manner
um so it's it's this is a solution to
the vanishing gradient but it's also
incredibly difficult to implement
correctly
um yeah so to escape the problem with
the decimals first layers oh and then
there's the other trick where
you uh you have known weights to what
works so at the very first layer you're
taking a successful model that
was that was processed somewhere else
and bolting on right at the beginning as
well
so you might remember we were talking
about morality at some point
and now we're not now we're talking
about hacking a machine to
get more i mean we we've we're off the
reservation at this point
but we're not going to stop because
there's too much money in it god damn it
and you're probably confused right you
started out with i just want to
calculate moral behavior right that's
all i want to do that can't be that damn
hard well it turns out it is um
because now you're fighting the limits
of the machine so calculating morality
is a
remarkably difficult task and we're
still hell-bent on doing it
of course well she knows the answer of
course we'll just add more layers
put her in charge and they'll just tweak
the
the the biases all day long and just
don't question anything it'll be fine
obviously duh they're all conspiracy
theorists if you disagree
um but that's just not it this there's
you're up against problems that involve
energy economics that's really what
you're fighting against
because even if you add more layers it
doesn't necessarily mean more
intelligence
and adding more data doesn't mean better
results either because
each one of these is a calculation
it takes energy to calculate these
things
this is expensive stuff i mean you may
have seen the uh the video
of mario brothers the character
um beating an ai training
mario to go through the first level of
mario brothers right
that cost ten thousand dollars to train
yeah yeah ten thousand right i can sit
my like a child in front of that
and feed it like a two dollar sandwich
and that child's gonna beat mario
brothers right
that's a the nerds have said ten
thousand dollars is an acceptable cost
to do this and we're not going to
question our a priori
uh uh concepts we're not going to
question our approach to this thing
we're just going to
bolt on more layers man we're doing it
we're just going to keep doing it we're
going to scale horizontally and just
make more gpus everywhere
and you can't that doesn't make things
more intelligent we've seen how
we've seen how it doesn't work right we
look at this right that's a mess
so instead of
taking this naive approach maybe it's
important to take the person with the
gun and get them out of the equation
let's get that person out of there right
because that person is
skewing the results they're they're
selecting for
criteria that is incorrect um they're
biasing the research
tremendously in their moral crusade just
get them out of here
just get rid of them because
they're interfering with actual progress
at this point um and
that that balance line right that's the
dollar sign that's that's the hard limit
we're up against
so there is one technique and this is
actually patented by google
so they actually did one thing right for
once this is called dropout
and dropout is a very interesting
technique
because they've accidentally made
a neural network perform the equivalence
of belief
and they don't know it yet so
what is dropout well we've seen how all
this stuff works how each one of these
lines is a weight and a bias
and that determines how this thing
categorizes which then is a weight and a
bias and categorizes and we end up with
our good evil
distribution percentage um
what if i knock one out
what if i knock two out what if i knock
that one out
so knockout is uh there there are
different rhythms to knock out you can
either
uh remove the node at random or at set
intervals or under different conditions
or whichever
so what this does this actually defeats
a very serious problem in your moral
assessments
where you may say well 256
has a pretty good non-violence rating
but according to hindus it does this
thing in population
if you go back a couple steps before the
knockouts and you say okay well
it turns out that these two things end
up being related somehow
so the inc so it is very feasible you
end up in a scenario where
the christian ranking and the islamic
ranking end up directly influencing one
another
and that's not a result you won because
now you're not getting a
good representation of either one of
these things you actually want these
two things to operate independently so
that you can get a proper assessment of
what they're doing
but if they end up in a scenario just
because of how the training worked or
the value that dealing with
they will end up sometimes in a scenario
where one's
ability to process will have an
interlocking
ability to interfere with this one's
processing as well so what you do is you
knock them out
by knocking them out the neural network
or the categorizational process i should
say
uh what it will do is it will find
paths around to actually go through and
say okay well i don't need that
dependency i'll
i'll redo it this way and so what you're
able to do is you're able to
curate these these hidden layers in a
way
to where it is your um you're
eliminating path dependency which is
another way of saying um
uh um
correlating correlating values which i
don't think is the right word i'm sorry
um so in doing this
what you're actually doing is more
similar to what the brain
is doing as opposed to anything else
that we looked at there's an entire army
of uh ai scientists who are convinced
the brain does back propagation
and back propagation is that that
vanishing gradient thing there's an
entire army
of people who are convinced that's what
our brain is doing and there's
absolutely no evidence
it's just it's all a hoax it's not real
um this
is more close to what the brain is doing
than anything else that i've seen in the
ai space
now why is that um because one
you're forcing the ais you're forcing a
categorizational process
to do more with less connections
so you're forcing it to be energy
efficient so instead of solving the
problem the way you want to solve it
because you're a moral
paragon and you never make mistakes
right instead of doing that
you say well let this thing solve it
but it doesn't solve the morality it
just solves the energy efficiency
which sounds a little weird you wouldn't
it's almost like deferring morality to
like an accountant
which can go wrong pretty bad pretty
quickly
but it turns out well each neuron is an
accountant too
it has its inputs of energy and it has
its outputs and it has its waste
so there's an accounting process in
every part of cognition
dropout allows us to say oh now there's
an accounting process here too
and so now we're getting more in sync
with how cognition actually works
through a drop-out process and
only and the only reason we're getting
close to that cognitive model is because
we're solving energy efficiency problems
we're not actually solving for morality
we're not fighting the network anymore
we're letting the network resolve energy
efficiency problems and that's how you
get
much better answers well this
discrimination because i
got damaged in his back because now i'm
knocking out hinduism and i can't talk
that knockout because i gotta represent
all the morality
i have to represent all of it at all
times but i get the vanishing gradient
problem
but then i can't solve it get these
people out of here
right they don't have the spinal
fortitude to handle
what has to be done so here's an example
of
of belief management is energy
effectiveness right so
imagine a world where we do what
um these moral police say and we have to
represent every moral conundrum possible
in our in our
categorizational process in order to
make any assessment whatsoever um
do you think our brain adds more neurons
on demand when we solve a problem
that's that'd be ludicrous in fact the
neuron itself
has uh has all the capacity to go
through mitosis it's all there the
dna is functioning nucleus is air it
just just doesn't
just doesn't cook at mitosis but imagine
if it did right you might think ah
well the neuron went through mitosis
we'd be super smart well
i just walked you through why it
wouldn't we just went through why that
wouldn't be the case
so it turns out the brain is dealing
with uh a non-scalable
machine in order to solve its problems
and let me give you a demonstration this
ball is a
whole bunch of photons bouncing off at a
brazilian events per second
and it's just being dumped in the brain
which is heavy dump in the brain
now meanwhile the poor brain is like
okay it's
but that's a lot of events per second
that's a brazilian i mean that's a big
number right it's so big it's not even a
word
it's it's it's nuts um and the brain is
already consuming 25
of the oxygen sweating it poor brain
right give it a break it doesn't need
all that stuff
geez work so hard for you you don't need
to do this to it
instead what if it turns out you only
needed that many
right what if you only needed that many
photons to get the exact same ball
well that's what the brain's done we
only get this many photons anyway from
our eyes
so we don't need all of the data we
don't need to represent the entirety of
reality to navigate reality
and that's okay because it's what we've
been doing the whole time joke's on us
so what's happening here is neural
evolution is actually relying on dropout
techniques
it's saying you don't need more neurons
you don't need to be connected
everywhere
we'll just route somewhere else we'll
connect to something else
we're going to give you or the the
neurons are
solving energy efficiency problems
they're not solving cognitive problems
they're not solving um logical problems
or speech problems or social problems
it is only solving energy efficiency
problems
that's all it's doing and just give an
example
good brain it's not sweating anymore you
can keep it you don't have to breathe
heavier because you saw a harder math
that'd be a weird relationship a bunch
of math kids just dying randomly during
tests that doesn't work
uh so
let's look at it as belief as technology
so what i'm going to declare is that
belief is actually path efficiency
because you're knocking out stuff you're
not adding more information you're
taking information away
that is the origin of a belief if i if
you had all the information there's
nothing to believe it's right there but
if i start stripping information out now
you have to make beliefs about it right
so it's it's a path of what we what
we're calling belief this whole time is
actually a path efficiency mechanism
so if we assume that these are you know
the nodes of the brain just for the sake
of
you know visualization um the symbols we
use the reality
they're not actually there's not some
homogenous sitting in the brain
like driving us right um each symbol is
a path
through the knocked out limitations
so every symbol you see in reality is
actually a
path that is carved from the belief
energy efficiency saving mechanism
even even the image you're looking at me
right now it takes 200 milliseconds
for you know this thing to move and then
it registers in your eyes it's going
through a lot of things it's not hitting
all your neurons it's hitting
a path of neurons and then it's changing
its direction it's changing it's it's
solving for the efficiency as it goes
through each one of those cognitive
subsystems
and uh we're
slowly getting there right now with our
ai because we've
finally played around with the knockout
process and this is
forcing this is indirectly creating
belief
as a technology um so instead of like
coding belief
what we're doing is we're emulating it
um
by taking away instead of constantly
adding to
so that's that's that's it that's what
happens when you apply morality to a
machine
you're put in this arms race where you
have to solve for energy efficiency
over the actual thing you went out to
solve for um and as a process
uh you accidentally create belief tada
that's it that's my talk
wow amazing all right everybody
this will be a good opportunity to start
preparing your questions and throw them
into the chat
i know that some were already written
but they're
kind of buried so feel free to write
them again if you still want to ask them
in the meantime i will get pat warmed up
with a couple of my own
so pat one thing that came up which
seems to be something of a theme
across all of your talks is that you're
pointing to this
idea that human beings want to but
ultimately can't
quantize reality um can you say more
about this like
where does this desire come from why is
it fundamentally flawed
uh what are the deeper motivations here
yeah
playing the game of this is 25 good this
is 70
bad has
it's ludicrous when you see that game
played out
and the reason is ludicrous is because
um
i said well welcome to whose line is it
anyway or all the
where the rules are made up and the the
score doesn't matter
you know kind of like that um
it's ludicrous because
if i got into interactions with you i
wouldn't know
where the line is just between you and i
and anyone else if it was just me and
you were chatting and doing the human
thing
i know where the line is i mean i have
my autism moments but i know damn well
where the line is and you know damn well
where the line is too
we don't need to sit there and formulate
it and draw it out and have a contract
and write it down
really need to do that thing if we're
going to walk away from each other
so if it's just you and i and you're
here we can we can hash this out and
figure it out but if i got to go over
there then i got to
represent this line that we already
established with one another and then i
got to enforce it and then i gotta build
this
legal system on top of it and i gotta it
we've seen what happens it results in
these
tremendous moments of gain a sort of
centralization
that's the most efficient way of
enforcing that type of mole
you know that moral emulation that we
call law or
the moral emulation that we find often
in theology
um and people are tilting at the wrong
windmill when they say oh religion
causes this and all
uh authority causes this that's not it's
that's not it we're trying to
we're trying to recreate the line that
that human beings naturally
have uh we're trying to recreate that in
abstractions
and it's messy it gets ugly it gets
weird we start fighting the machine
right we're
instead of trying to represent the moral
equilibrium that we had with one another
during that very organic exchange
now we're no longer solving for that
we're fighting the machine just as we do
with vanishing gradient um so i think
i i think it's
i mean my brother's in jail that's not
helping
i certainly have some beef on that um
and i can explain all the socioeconomic
factors on that one too
um but but independent of my own
personal experience
i think what we're what we're
we have this instinct to quantize
morality and put a little box around
each action
and give it a wait about what's good and
bad and then someone comes along and
says well kick that dictator out now
it's my turn to label the weights and
then everybody wants to label the
weights now you end up with never-ending
posting on the internet and then
it's 2020 and you can't leave your house
and you have problems um
a common theme that comes up in a lot of
the sessions at the stoa
is this idea of the different types of
knowing and in particular
there's uh there's basically the sense
that we're over
indexing on propositional knowing um
[Music]
painting reality in terms of highly
legible
well-formulated words and concepts
uh but i think there's a lot of people
here that have an intuition and that's a
key word
that that is missing something it's
missing a huge piece and what you just
said there is that
two people can kind of intuitively even
say intuitive but
we know where the line is can you speak
a little bit more about
where does that line that intuition is
my word but that intuition of that moral
equilibrium come from
and why do humans have that ability
yeah we're social animals so as a result
you know emotions evolved probably
exclusively like
roll back the clock 50 000 years and
it's just a bunch of people
sitting somewhere fighting nature and
each other to a degree
and we have maybe 200 words maybe tops
we're still conveying stuff that's
useful i mean yeah i can't send you a
google link and i can't you know
argue pull up the dictionary and say you
know this but
we're still conveying information that
we need to do our
daily survival so i need to convey to
you that
i'm feeling exhausted i'm not going to
invent new words and then explain to you
how i'm exhausted i'm going to
you know i'm going to have the physical
behavior about my being and you're going
to be able to read that and see that and
go oh
okay we'll take the heavy load off that
person put on that person now we've
solved
the tribal problem because the one
individual was honestly conveying
the emotional social data that was
needed to make the tribal assessment
and and we see this in animals in terms
of how
group animals also operate in the same
manner
you see in schools of fish one fish
turns they all turn right so
we're conveying the behavior between one
another at all times and emotions are
one
one way in which that's uh that whole
decoding encoding process works but
there's other ways to convey it we found
a way to convey it with writing or we
convey it with all these other
abstractions
um the older i get the more i hate
language
that's i think that's i'm going to be a
crotchety old man that hates language
i'm going to
be a post-modernist i'm going to say
deconstruct all language i don't know i
don't know
um but i think it's uh
i think
the conveyance of knowing what knowing
where the line is is a byproduct that
that moral equilibrium
is naturally derived to um as we are
engaging the encoding decoding
of emotional behavior and if that's
removed
then you when you learn to live without
it or
uh you emulate it you come up with these
proxies for it
and now we're on zoom right this is all
a proxy for
emotional conveyance is what we're doing
right now
is it good enough is it the real thing i
mean it's good enough
but it's not the real thing so
we have approximations it's just
approximations all the way down
which sucks because all we want to do is
just be in the same room and drink
around a fire
i think that's it yeah that's uh it's
very accurate
very much how i'm feeling right now
okay last question for me kind of
segways from that
with your model how do you think uh how
would you say
psychedelics like psilocybin influence
the dropout techniques
that you are suggesting that the human
mind is continually doing
the only mind-altering chemical i've
ever taken is alcohol
i have never done drugs never um
so i don't know i can't speak from an
experience point
so i have to defer to people who have
researched that
and there's there's different
qualities of research on that point
you'll have
the experimental anecdotal stuff um
but unfortunately that's all tied into
the moral machine work too because of
drug trade
and drug flow and drug regulation so as
a result people end up lying about their
experiences
you don't get honest insights people are
people enjoy the high but they are
forced to rationalize it even if it
their life up
um so it's a bit of a it's hard to get
true readings on there so then you're
forced to look at other types of
research maybe big pharma research or
government research or black budget
jeffrey epstein style stuff
and you end up in all kinds of
experiments to drop out stuff we do it
with mice for example when you start
knocking out parts of the brain
uh at the genetic level you actually
just
deny the dna from ever growing that part
of the brain so
we do knock out experiments there too
regarding drugs that do it lsd was
supposed to be this wonder drug it was
supposed to make superhumans because
this is all derivative of humanist
garbage where
they think that the mind is infinitely
plastic and if you make it
more plastic then you get more
intelligence but
that's not it either you don't get more
intelligence from more plasticity
because there's still
it's an energy efficiency problem still
that's all it is so
i've seen what these guys have done i
mean there's stuff like mkultra
where they oh we can change the
plasticity we can change how things are
connected and we can do it through
trauma-based training or we can do it by
slipping lsd and every single cia
agent's coffee just wouldn't last
it gets it gets ludicrous um
you do find things about human nature
though it's not it's not that all the
research was terrible
um most of it was but the
uh what you do get from is an
understanding of trying to
turn a human being's mind into a machine
which is the purpose of that research to
begin with
that's the idea of like trying to
understand how to
[Music]
uh get the mind in a suggestible state
to then retrain the pavlovian responses
to then respond to
an input an encoded input a associative
input and then have the behavior out in
the desired manner
so that's ultimately where that level of
research goes and
that's even just as skewed as the drug
law research
so behind each and every one of it is
still the agenda of power seeking
and it's it's really the
research like
like i'm an advocate of like abstract
math from the 1800s where the
mathematicians just studied math for the
sake of studying math
uh there was no application for their
research whatsoever
and as a result you ended up with this
huge huge huge explosion
of technological capabilities by the
1900s
i think if we're studying human
psychology and remove the power element
out of it then you might get a very
equivalent
golden era as well yeah that
definitely seems to be a common theme uh
power corrupting okay so i'm gonna start
to pick some questions from the chat
uh janelle would you like to read your
question
feel free to unmute yourself and just go
for it
if you're still there all right
i'm gonna pass it to
rachel would you like to read your
question
hi yeah i was just curious about your
view on
virtual reality with this talk about
psychedelics on different worlds
separation how do you view virtual
reality and what steps do you think um
we're going to achieve with it in the
future
that is a fantastic question i have had
the joy of experiencing this one
firsthand i'm going to tell a story it's
going to be
disturbing and then it's going to be
funny so there's this room
there's this one app called vr chat
that's where the
uganda knuckles meme came from um this
is a chat room where everybody can
change their avatar to be anything
up to and including serial killers or
the blue screen of death from windows
i've seen that in that game
and uh they just have social
interactions they sit around and they
do the social thing um but what's most
interesting about it
is that it's not the internet we're used
to
uh the internet we're used to at least i
might be speaking as an old man i'm used
to
text-based internet right you type all
the time and
you come up with these linguistic
extraction abstractions to represent
yourself
and then nobody reads it right and then
it's endless flame wars that's the
internet i come
from the virtual reality space was
totally alien
because people could interact in a way
that was pretty
high resolution replication of human
interaction
as best you could because uh the feet
problems still exist
they haven't done the feet quite well
yet but they've got the hands and the
head pretty good
and they have emulations of the upper
torso correct and that matters for body
language
and that's the missing dimension that a
lot of internet use has
that body language element is in oh man
it changes everything and here's where
i'm going with this
so i'm in the room and i'm just cracking
jokes and being myself and someone
comes up and says hey let me show you
let me take you to this private spot and
whatever goes there and it's like this
room that he made
and well manicured like it was this
project and you really care about it he
did a good job
uh then he invited me to this other
thing and i always end up at this part
of the internet i don't know
it's not my thing i just end up there
whether it's 4chan or anything end up at
the part of the internet where it's a
bunch of dudes dressed up as anime girls
i don't know how this keeps happening
i'm not asking for this i'm not putting
whatever i'm putting out there whatever
um so it's just a bunch of like 40 year
old dudes like hey bro nice
nice uh nice motto you got there i think
they're all like modelers or something
they're in the end i don't know
i just find anime internet all the
goddamn time
and uh in this room of what would widely
be considered social rejects
the highest order even their pecking
orders uh
uh formed naturally and they form
naturally because of the body language
not because of linguistics or because
you have an admin little symbol or
because of your roles and permissions or
because you're well liked
straight up body language was the
uh was the formation of the pecking
order
so and i can say this because there was
one person there who did not say a word
everybody else was talking and getting
to know each other and doing the social
thing except this one character
he did not say a word not a single
word
and i don't i wasn't a boy it was a guy
i don't know what it was i have no idea
they didn't say a word so you can't
really tell it's just
it's anime girl but a high resolution
model this person had to have had a
vocab set up
absolutely had to because she was
dancing around she was doing all these
things
so she had the full access of body
language where everyone else didn't and
because of that difference that that
asymmetrical difference
the pecking order revolved around her
just from that alone
and i found that fascinating i was like
oh man
oh man this is the future of politics i
know it i see it it's coming
this is it so vr is is going to
create a high resolution access point to
emu to
recreating that moral equilibrium that i
was talking about earlier
all right uh alexander lee would you
like to unmute yourself and ask your
question
yeah thanks for your discussion pat
my question is um do you see this drop
out feature as being somewhat equivalent
to
a verveiki's salience landscape
i do not know that one please please uh
please give me a summary
uh okay so raviki uh introduces it
in a variety of ways it actually comes
out of autism research
in psychology the idea is the salience
landscape is basically a metaphorical
construct to
describe the configurations of how
people
notice things in their environment and
situation so
it's an explanation for how different
emotional cues
mappings and meanings can be constructed
out of the different aspects
that people notice so you know
everybody has a different salience
landscape and the difference in salience
landscape
can contribute to meaning making and as
you develop
as a person you
can develop your salience landscape so
that's that's directly connected to
for reiki's discussion how do you find
relevancy
and how do you develop wisdom that's a
very good
analogy i would say the idea of
going through and using knockout to
curate the results you are effectively
curating that salience landscape that's
a good that's a good way of putting that
i think knockout because you can't keep
track of everything
there's there's too much information
going on at all times it's mostly noise
biology does a fantastic job in
filtering down what
it should be looking for and you
probably want to check up hoffman's
um ted talk about that regarding
uh why we don't see reality and what
we're actually filtering from it is
primarily mating signals
because the moment any simulated life
started seeing reality it was dead in
three generations
because it wasn't looking for any it
wasn't looking to reproduce it was too
busy looking at the atoms
so it wasn't able to find mating signals
and keep going
so i think um by the very nature of
cognitive evolution itself here
it's all knockout uh in terms of data
availability
um you just don't have access to
everything and that
will that will change
i mean what you see is what you're
exposed to as an influence and stuff and
what you're not exposed to also
influences you too
and that landscape mechanism is a good
explanation of explaining that outside
of my little
network spasm that happened 20 minutes
ago
um how do you develop wisdom from that
[Music]
that's a hard question because i i live
in a time in which wisdom doesn't exist
so i don't know that answer that
question
well i mean viveki um i mean when you
when you involve other people
and ultimately it's about coordination
between other people so
a wisdom is maybe can be defined in some
way as
having a salience landscape that's
flexible enough to notice
what's relevant to other people i see i
see
cross overlap
is that sufficient is it sufficient
enough to leave is it sufficient enough
to do your own knockouts
meaning remove that yeah it's good
practice to conduct your own self
knockouts
um it's very good practice in fact to
say okay i know how this model works now
i have to take everything i know about
that model and get rid of it
start from scratch because i may have
missed something
if you get too complacent on a subject
you may miss developments on it that
could be a good definition
i think you'll work with that cool
thanks
so we are approaching 9 30 but there's
still a couple more questions in the
chat
uh normally we do go over this mark um
because of the energy and the
conversation pat are you still get to
stay on for
the 10 15 minutes okay great um
okay uh julian would you like to share
your question
uh sure um let me just read it easier
so it's pretty similar to alexander's i
think
um so i'll read it out i said are you
aware of any
systematic programmable approaches to
analyzing
the different results from different
knockout neural network solves
where the learnings from these analysis
can be applied to other areas fields
without having to rerun the new neural
network sort of like what our brain does
does that make sense it does the
the knockout formulation the the
knockout networks
are usually applied to solve very
specific problems
that's one of the bigger challenges of a
lot of the the neural network
development is that everything is
very artisanal there's no general
solution
quite yet you have to really tune and
get everything so there's plenty of
differentials out there
but they're all tailored to the specific
domain of a very specific problem
so you won't be able to scale that up to
the completeness of human cognition
okay yeah because i've just been
thinking about that sort of thing for a
while and have never really
managed to come up with any solution
yeah it's it's a tough one
but the the knockout that i'm
recommending as
uh the energy efficiency
which is ultimately i'm using knockout
and energy efficiency as kind of a
transferable concept here or a trend a
concept of transitive
properties between it
[Music]
the the knockout is just as it is in the
neural space it's happening in very
local systems
in the brain as well um when when you
have two neurons and they're connected
and that connection breaks
that's a knockout yeah it's connected
somewhere else so that's
that's how you put one thing the path
the path is reformed
so you get uh you get different symbols
or you get different intensities or
different
experiences as well um but at the
but if that is that scale invariant the
answer is no
it's not it can't be because it's not as
if i'm taking my brain and literally
pulling it out and then thinking about
stuff and putting i can't i can't knock
out entire
regions of my brain uh safely at least
um
like i suppose alcohol does its best but
for the most part i don't i i'm not
seeing
knockout at a systemic level it's it's
primarily local
okay thank you i i'm wondering pat
if this idea that knockouts
and beliefs are more than just analogous
like there's something
something deeper behind it are we taking
steps towards
building machines with belief systems
we are not consciously doing that
i am of the opinion that the machines
control so much of our economy
that they're doing it for us that sounds
ludicrous i'm out here saying that oh my
god these machines will never
reach human consciousness yes that's
true um
but again we're solving for energy
efficiency that's
all that's ever being solved for so
when we defer our stock market to high
frequency trading algorithms
we say here keep our numbers up
regardless of what we're doing
regardless of our actual
productivity we just need to keep the
numbers up because
god damn it all those 401ks you don't
want them sinking or it's going to be
bloodbath everywhere so now we said here
ai solved this for us now we go to
google and
say hey solve our morality for us
because this is too messy and we don't
want to be liable
we have all these political ambitions
but we just don't want to be caught
doing it
so can we just defer this to uh the
machine and then they can do it for us
so now we're deferring that right and
then we go to politics and we say well
we know what cambridge analytica can do
it can alter the reality tunnel of
individual people
uh ideally a small competition space
such as a
uh an electoral college which is only 5
000 people that's very easy to target
so now you defer your your influence
operations to ai as well which then
extends naturally to marketing
so before you know it your entire
civilizational infrastructure is at
has been influenced in one capacity or
another
by these machines which aren't even
cognizant
now you might say well we still control
the machines i don't think so
i don't think we control the
anymore i think they have
steered
so many prime parts of our economy and
our civilization
that they are now running the show
effectively now they're not consciously
doing it it's not a conspiracy it's not
like they show up in the smoky back room
of some
i don't know dark web website and go ha
ha how do we make the humans go it's not
like that at all
it's more like it's it's it's flip
it's past the inflection point where
our behavior has been so systematized
into certain activities where you wake
up you go to work you make your money
you have your fund
you consume you go to sleep right that's
basically the cycle
of of being a member of an
industrialized civilization
you have to produce you have to consume
some people get to be over consumers
some people get to be overproducers but
the distribution
you know you can argue the distribution
all day long but that's roughly it
if you reduce human potential down to
just that vector
it's very easy for these machines to say
if i control this point
then the humans will then channel
resources into me
so now the question is which one of
these ais
wins is really what i'm asking because
is it going to be the financial ai's
are they able to steer human behavior
into dumping resources into it
will it be the influence ais will be the
political ais
what happens when religion gets involved
it's coming it's going to be
weird but it's coming
uh memetic caper can you ask your
question
hi uh what happens uh when there's too
much energy efficiency
in a neural net does the ring the range
of inputs
that don't gener generate category
errors that shrinks
like you get to uh you sort of get a
tunnel vision in your
um algorithm yep that's called over
training
so that's overfitting that's the that's
the term for it
that's where you are you are correcting
for
such a narrow problem that it's just
easier to write
an algorithm to do it instead
okay so it's like once you get over
fitting
you should just stop using machine
learning is what you're saying
basically yes the cost benefit analysis
has to be made whether do we just keep
tuning this model or is our problem
actually as small as we think it is or
have we looked at our training sets
incorrectly you start asking a bunch of
questions about again solving your own
energy efficiency in the form of
allocating resources
okay all right thank you
all right marshall do you want to ask
about the machine elves
uh sure um well actually you know what i
think that uh
david swedlow had some good questions
and i think that he should totally ask
because mine was kind of posting
out loud so
let's let him do it i appreciate that
uh david feel free to unmute yourself
and ask a question
it's almost i'm almost scared of the
sense
so i'm going to ask this this is kind of
a this is a thought experiment
and as a question um if i think of what
a neuron is doing
individual neuron and this is based
partly on on reading
um sapolsky and behave
it's it's a kind of a model of of
plato's cave
it's trying to make sense of the shadows
on the wall and effectively
the firing of the neuron is when it can
no longer effectively model the outside
world and it must actually go out into
the world and see what's happening
and update its map of the wall and i
think that human beings are doing
something similar
we live in our little cave until we
can't stand it till the noise is so much
that we're effectively where
where and that what um boulder yard
talks about with
the desert of the reel our our systems
can no longer make sense of the
that this the algorithms are so poorly
modeling our reality
based on overfittedness that we have to
come out of our caves
and effectively i think that's where we
are right now so something like
wisdom cultivation feels like this kind
of fractal
updating of my internal maps of the cave
on the wall and coming out and actually
saying okay what the is really
going on
that's right yeah it does make sense in
fact uh
that goes back to the calculating your
loss um
where your your categorization error has
hit your threshold
and saying this is no longer acceptable
i need to do something
to either my experiences but we're
always we're always modifying our brains
we just don't know it
um you have an experience you're
modifying your brain it's not like your
brain is this box and it's like
immutable it's
it's you know it's rewiring itself as it
goes so
um the models that we use come from
our symbol efficiency tricks so when i
look at that ball
that's in the slide a couple a couple 10
10 20 minutes ago
um that ball is there in its own space
but now it's in my mind
as a path efficiency it's there it's
it's
baked in and now i can go down the path
i can reconstruct the memory of the ball
so i have the model of the ball
available but if the ball disappears
my model needs to be updated so my
categorization
where the ball is is now wrong so i
gotta modify either
my biases i can't do self surgery on
individual neurons so what i do is i
just steer my body to go find the ball
i'm gonna go find it right so there are
thresholds in which the models do go out
of whack and we have a whole range of
corrective behavior to engage
just just a quick update on that in some
sense when i think about that
what each neuron actually is doing is
way
more complex than what brain scientists
tend to think that they're doing
you know they're just now starting to
say wait a minute it looks like it's
actually
not only is a brain on a neuron cell
isn't just a neural network
node it's it's doing exclusive or
in the dendrites so it's doing something
way
more complicated than a single bit
that that energy efficiency is going to
compound into its structure itself
yeah absolutely i would agree with that
all right this might be our last
question
unless somebody has something really
someone really eager has something else
next arya can you unmute yourself and
ask your question
hey pat thanks for the talk it's pretty
cool
um i had a question about how you would
factor an intent
into the moral machines uh would you
think something like an adversarial
approach could work
where instead of having an adversarial
machine you had an adversarial human
and their job was to try and fool the
machine of its intent
and then this like fullness intent
fullness factor was added into the lost
function and
the game continued from there what
problems do you see you are skipping
ahead to the end
sir you should not be listening further
um
what you are describing is my butterfly
war effectively
my butterfly war was the ability to make
these moral machines
make mistakes uh the ability to
they were out there chasing certain
moral causes um
in this case the the material the
western material humanist cause of
of i can even call it liberal democracy
it's more like
um never-ending extensions of
middle-class 1960s as a moral framework
whatever word that is
um uh and what i said was if you target
certain data sets
then you can confuse the ai into
actually targeting the things it wants
to protect
using exclusively moral machine analysis
alone
uh this put me on a bunch of radars boy
did my life change
because that wasn't supposed to happen
but apparently it did
and so what happens what what happens
when you play that game where you have
an absolute human
in the space and they are now steering
the machine indirectly and there's
nothing you can do
you can't program it to not do that um
because if you do so then let's take my
example where i say well
uh certain morality actions are being
punished and certain morality behaviors
are not
so therefore if the people are being
punished can demonstrate the veneer of
the moral behaviors that are not
well then there you go that's your
protection that's way better than the
cafe antivirus
that's way better than a vpn now you can
be yourself you just have this fully
automated layer of crap
that the ai then let's pass because well
i'm trying to
i'm trying to solve my moral causes and
do my moral things and as a result they
would then have to attack actual people
demonstrating that veneer who they're
actually trying to protect but they're
more
with their moral engine so the whole
thing just goes belly up as a result
um but if you step if you
apply that to what i said about the ais
are already in control
and they're competing to get resources
and using us to get those resources
the one i'm talking about here is
effectively a eugenic multiplier
between the ai's
so remember these ais certain ones live
and certain ones die which ones die
well the ones that are underfunded ones
that are built on a bad business model
the ones that are um
incapable of channeling human energy
into the resources to keep it alive
ais die all the time they don't get
funding they
lose a cloud connection their team goes
belly up
happens all the time so certain ones
naturally select
and certain ones don't so now we're
playing the the darwinian game there's a
natural selection element going on in ai
survival
and what butterfly does is it acts as
eugenic multiplier
the same way that camouflage
but why i picked the butterfly the same
way that butterfly acts as a eugenic
multiplier as well
you'll see that the butterfly when it
takes its wing patterns
uh it's doing that to fool the
predator's tongue
we didn't learn that until like way
someone actually ate a butterfly and
said this is rather sour
um it turns out that when the predator
eats the butterfly it comes to the same
conclusion
he says wow this thing tastes like crap
but because there's so many bright
colors associated with it the last thing
it sees are those bright colors before
it closes its mouth
so then it associates those bright
colors with the toxic taste
and so it ignores the bright colors and
then other species that aren't
butterflies start
generating those colors by the way
mammals lizards flowers they start
generating that color because they're
selecting in a way that well the
predator doesn't eat that color
then i'm making the decision obviously
it's not how natural selection works
but it is a eugenics multiplier things
get to survive that otherwise should not
because this one thing tasted bad the
predator has been sold
so the answer to your question is
natural selection
eugenics in the game of camouflage
that's where it ends
if you try to impose an intent in these
moral machines what i'm saying
yeah do you think if enough of us uh
started playing the game of fooling
intent we would just engage in this like
infinite game with the machines
yes correct cool
thanks
all right hannah take us home ask us the
last question
um so my understanding of thought is
i roughly call it a pavlovian model
and my understanding is something like
each neural pathway becomes
the more probable pathway for thought
every time you take it sort of like
wearing in a hiking trail
and so i'm sort of curious on your
thoughts on this model and how it
corresponds to what you've been talking
about today yeah the um the
pavlovian training repetition exposure
um again it's a path efficiency what
you're describing
it's not that the path is being selected
intentionally in this case you're
overriding the efficiencies and forcing
one into play
so instead of letting the brain come up
with these conclusions of what's good
around it
that would be a way of imposing intent
uh into the moral machine of the brain
the same way if you try to force
uh weights and biases into
a neural network you get things you have
to come up with this very complicated
effectively therapy to fix the the moral
machine
and the same is true about pavlovian
responses if you if you train someone
through repetition
on these on certain domains um
there are costs that are seen in their
behavior and you have to engage in
serious therapy don't do it
thank you
all right thank you so much everyone for
participating
uh feel free to click the zoom reaction
button and clap for pat ryan
or you can snap your fingers in the kind
of cringy way that people tend to do on
zoom
um thanks again pat ryan for another
amazing session at the dark stoa
[Music]
i'm just going to mention a couple
things about what's happening at the
stoa
for everybody here so
if i can pull it all up
so uh there's a there's an event coming
up with
david fuller from rebel wisdom and
imagine a lot of the people in
attendance here are familiar with rebel
wisdom
it's sense-making journalism in the
liminal war and it's going to be at 1 pm
eastern on tuesday
and peter and david fuller will be
discussing
a recent rebel wisdom talk that they had
and also
just uh one thing to for people who
don't know
the stoa has a series of recurring
events kind of like this one that
happens every friday
uh that we call the wisdom gym and if
you go to the stoa.ca you can figure out
which one of those events you want to
plug into and their are mastermind
groups there
are meditation exercises and all sorts
of things
so check that out uh and the final thing
i'll say is the stow is a gift
um and this is our gift to you
and if you feel like you have a gift to
give in return
you can do so at the website that i'm
going to put in the chat below
all right thanks everybody
see you all soon